Guide to the Frank W. Crane Photograph Collection 1901-1913 PR 128
New-York Historical Society
Frank W. Crane photograph collection
1901-1913
New-York Historical Society
Crane, Frank W., 1867-1953.
PR 128
1 Linear feet (2 boxes)
The Frank W. Crane Photograph Collection spans the period from 1901 to 1913 and contains photographs of New York City and of trees throughout the city and New England.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frank W. Crane, February 28, 1945.
Arrangement
Negatives are filed by N-YHS assigned numbers. Most negatives were titled by Crane. N-YHS-assigned descriptive titles appear in brackets. Prints are arranged into two subseries: Numbered and Unnumbered. Numbered photos follow the numbering in Series I. Unnumbered prints are arranged by geographical subject.
Biographical Note
Frank W. Crane was born in Connecticut in 1867, and moved to New York City with his family several years later. He graduated from Columbia University in 1890 and then worked as a reporter for the New York Times from 1894 to 1945. He wrote about many topics, including golf, rare coins, and automobiles, but toward the end of his tenure at the Times he wrote mainly about real estate and the changing nature of New York City's built environment. He was active in the Greenwich Village Historical Society. Crane died in 1953.
Scope and Contents
The Frank W. Crane Photograph Collection spans the period from 1901 to 1913 and contains photographs of New York City and of trees throughout the city and New England. The collection is divided into two series by format: Negatives; and Prints.
Gelatin silver prints.; negatives (photographs); Buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Historic trees -- New York (State) -- New York.; Parks -- New York (State) -- New York.; Photography of trees.
- Series I: Negatives
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. Negatives consists of ninety-four nitrate film negatives taken between 1904 and 1913. The negatives are numbered, although in no discernible order; this was probably done by a New-York Historical Society staff member at the time of accession. They are listed here in numerical order. One third of the negatives have corresponding prints. Those without corresponding prints are noted as such in the container list. Because these are nitrate negatives, they have been physically removed from the collection and are kept separately in cold storage. If you need to access the negatives, please contact a staff member in the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections for assistance.
  - C-1: Yard of Van Buren house, W. side of 14th St., between Fifth and Sixth Aves., 1911 May (Box 1)
  - C-2: N.W. corner of Hudson and Houston Sts. looking west toward Houston, 1910 Dec. (Box 1)
    General note
    No vintage print
  - C-3: Old houses, 15-17 Dominick Street, north side between Clark and Varick, 1910 Dec. (Box 1)
  - C-4: S.W. corner Hudson and Christopher Sts., 1910 Dec. (Box 1)
  - C-5: Old houses, 1 and 2 State St. [Seaman's Church Institute], 1911 Feb. (Box 1)
  - C-6: Old house, corner of Prince and Lafayette Sts, Monroe's home, where he died, 1911 Feb. (Box 1)
  - C-7: Greenwich Hall, 501 Hudson, N.W. corner of Hudson and Christopher Sts., looking up Hudson, row of 5 old houses adjoining hall, 1910 Dec. (Box 1)
  - C-8: Fourth Ave. side of Madison Square Garden, between 26 and 27 Sts., 1911 June (Box 1)
  - C-9: Old shacks, N. side 64th St. west of Central Park West; 23 Crimmins Tavern, adjoining at 21 Central Park Gardens, 1911 Aug. (Box 1)
  - C-10: Old wooden houses, N.W. corner of Jackson and Front Sts., corner 77 Jackson, 4 in block about to be torn down, 1911 Aug. (Box 1)
  - C-11: Old Van Buren House and portion of yard looking east on 14th St., 1911 Aug. (Box 1)
  - C-12: Old Schermerhorn House, University Place, 1911 May (Box 1)
  - C-13: Shanty and refreshment booth, S.E. corner of Fifth Ave. and 90th St., opposite Carnegie Museum, 1911 Oct. (Box 1)
  - C-14: Row of old houses, N. side Canal St., 461-473 Canal St. between Hudson and Varick Sts., 1910 Dec. (Box 1)
  - C-15: 7 State St., and along State, looking East [Mission of Our Lady of the Rosary], 1911 Feb. (Box 1)
  - C-16: Jones Lane at South Street, 53 South St. at N.W. corner, 1911 Feb. (Box 1)
  - C-17: N.W. corner of South and DePeyster Sts., 1911 Feb. (Box 1)
  - C-18: N.W. corner Wall and South Sts., 1911 Feb. (Box 1)
  - C-19: 69-71 Charlton St., N. side, between Hudson and Varick Sts., 1910 Dec. (Box 1)
  - C-20: Old homes, N. side of Bleecker St. facing Hancock, 207-209 Bleecker St., on N.E. corner at Minetta Lane, 1910 Dec. (Box 1)
  - C-21: N.W. corner of Sullivan and Watts Sts., wooden buildings and junk shop, 1910 Dec. (Box 1)
  - C-22: Colonnade row opposite Astor Library, 1911 Feb. (Box 1)
  - C-23: Cushman's old store, N.E. corner of 10th St. and Greenwich Ave., looking down 10th St., 1911 Feb. (Box 1)
  - C-24: Old Schermerhorn's Mansion, N. side of 23rd St. opposite Stern's; taken just as beginning to tear down, 1911 May (Box 1)
  - C-25: E. side of Beekman Place from 49th to 51st Sts., 1911 June (Box 1)
  - C-26: Old Shot Tower between 53rd and 54th Sts., near Ave. A and East River, taken from 54th St., 1911 June (Box 1)
  - C-27: Old houses, 107-109 W. 11th St., E. of Fourth Ave., 1911 May (Box 1)
  - C-28: Old houses, 93-95 Morton St., N. side between Greenwich and Washington; torn down Spring 1911, 1910 Dec. (Box 1)
  - C-29: Hoguet House, Riverside Dr. between 142nd and 143rd Sts., 1909 Dec. (Box 1)
  - C-30: Old Latimer House, Third Ave., E. side between 90th and 91st Sts.], 1904 (Box 1)
  - C-31: West Presbyterian Church, 27 W. 42nd; torn down Summer 1911, 1910 Aug. (Box 1)
  - C-32: Old houses, N.E. corner of Seventh Ave. and 33rd St., 1910 July (Box 1)
  - C-33: St. John's Chapel, Varick St., 1904 (Box 1)
  - C-34: Old shanty and garden, S.W. corner of West End Ave. and 95th St., 1905 Aug. (Box 1)
  - C-35: Close up of shanty, S.W. corner of West End Ave. and 95th St., 1905 Aug. (Box 1)
  - C-36: Old Slip Hotel, N.W. corner and South St., 1911 Feb. (Box 1)
  - C-37: Jas B. Clews Residence, N.E. corner of Fifth Ave. and 85th St.], 1911 June (Box 1)
  - C-38: N.E. corner Varick and Charlton, corner house John Hulster Pharmacy, 172 Varick St., 1911 Feb. (Box 1)
  - C-39: N. side Charlton St. adjoining N.E. corner of Varick St., first house is 53 Charlton St., Christopher Columbus University of N.Y. City; 5 houses alike, 1911 Feb. (Box 1)
  - C-40: Gramercy Park North, 1911 June (Box 1)
  - C-41: Old wooden house, N.W. corner of 181st St. and Broadway, 1910 (Box 1)
  - C-42: N.E. corner Varick and King Sts., corner house 190 Varick St., fourth house from corner King Social Club, 1911 Feb. (Box 1)
  - C-43: John Q. Wendel House and Dr. Isaac Kip House beyond, N.W. corner of Fifth Ave. and 39th St., 1911 June (Box 1)
  - C-44: Corlear's Hook Park [Manhattan tower of Williamsburg Bridge visible in Background], 1911 Apr. (Box 1)
  - C-45: Percy R. Pyne's new house, N.W. corner of Park Ave. and 68th St., 1911 June (Box 1)
  - C-46: Old buildings on Fourth Ave. from N.W. corner of 28th St., 406-410 Fourth Ave., etc., 1911 June (Box 1)
  - C-47: Old Shot tower and Arden House, 54th St., 1903 (Box 1)
  - C-48: Row wooden houses, N.W. corner of 86th St. and Park Ave., 1911 June (Box 1)
  - C-49: Kedalta's house, N.W. corner of Second Ave. and St. Mark's Place, 1911 May (Box 1)
  - C-50: Old residences, 1-9 West 47th St. west of Fifth Avenue, 1911 June (Box 1)
  - C-51: Old houses, Ave. A between 60th and 61st Sts., W. side, 1906 (Box 1)
  - C-52-54: Old Smith house, 61st St., 1903 (Box 1)
  - C-55: Old Smith house, 61st St. [with woman], 1903 (Box 1)
  - C-56: T.P. Ryan's former residence, N.W. corner Fifth Ave. and 12th St., undated (Box 1)
  - C-57: Isaac Brokaw house, N.W. corner Fifth Ave. and 79th St., 1905 (Box 1)
  - C-58: W. side Lafayette Pl. opposite old Astor Library showing old Colonnade Row, 1911 June (Box 1)
  - C-59-60: Old Rhinelander Row, W. side Seventh Ave. between 12th and 13th Sts., 1911 May (Box 1)
  - C-61-62: [Battery Park, elevated railroad track in foreground], [1905] (Box 1)
  - C-63: [Horse-drawn lawn mower, Battery Park?], [1905] (Box 1)
  - C-64-67: [Fire at 4 South Street], undated (Box 1)
  - C-68: [View of crowd from above], undated (Box 1)
  - C-69: [Dirigible], undated (Box 1)
  - C-70: [Municipal ferry, New York City to Staten Island], [1905] (Box 1)
  - C-71: [Spy Oak, Westchester], 1906 June (Box 1)
  - C-72-73: [Pell Oak, Bronx, Pelham Bay Park], 1906 June (Box 1)
  - C-74-75: [76 Stone House, Tappan, N.Y. Used as Major Andre's prison in the Revolutionary War], undated (Box 1)
  - C-76: [Big Elm, in front of Neal's store, Stockbridge, Mass.], 1904 Aug. (Box 1)
  - C-77: [Big Elm and Casino, Stockbridge, Mass.], 1904 Aug. (Box 1)
  - C-78: [Big Elm in front of Peck House, Stratford, Conn.], 1904 Aug. (Box 1)
  - C-79: [Elms on Main Street, Stockbridge, Mass.], 1904 Aug. (Box 1)
  - C-80-81: [Monument to Thomas Paine with bust], undated (Box 1)
    No vintage prints
  - C-82-83: [Unidentified monument with bust], undated (Box 1)
  - C-84: Esther [Crane's wife], 1913 June (Box 1)
  - C-85: [Unidentified tree], undated (Box 1)
  - C-86: [Unidentified house], undated (Box 1)
  - C-87: [Unidentified view of park with children in foreground], undated (Box 1)
  - C-88-89: [Unidentified house], undated (Box 1)
  - C-90: Old Van Buren House, 21 W. 14th St., 1911 Oct. (Box 1)
  - The Alpine near Broadway & 33rd St. & McAlpine back to 34th St. (tomorrow fall of 1910), 1910 July (Box 1)
  - 2 Side Park Ave. from 52nd St., Old Piano Factory between 52nd & 53rd, 1911 July (Box 1)
  - [riverboats], [1910] (Box 1)
  - [street scenes with trolley cars and horse and buggies], [1910] (Box 1)
- Series II. Prints
  Series II. Prints contains 160 silver gelatin photographs. Thirty prints of New York City are numbered to correspond with the negatives. Others (primarily views of trees throughout New York State and New England) are arranged by geographical subject. Most of the photographs are 3 x 4 inches, a few are as large as 5 x 7 inches, and some are mounted on card.
  The series includes views of New York City, mainly focusing on old wood-frame buildings, older residences, and street scenes including them. Some include beverage sign advertisements, particularly for Moxie. About half of the photographs in the collection are images of trees. Unnumbered photos of parks in Manhattan show trees and general park scenes in Central Park, East River Park, City Hall Park, Stuyvesant Square and Riverside Park.Photos of specific trees in Manhattan show those on the Hamilton, Jumel, and Audubon estates.
  Other New York photos show trees in Prospect Park, Brooklyn, Queens and the Bronx. Photos of historic or interesting trees in Connecticut and Massachusetts are also included. A set of family photos from Twilight Park in the Catskills in New York shows the general landscape, Crane's family, and amusingly, a photo of a woman chopping at a tree with an axe.
  - Subseries II.A. Numbered Prints
    - C-1: Yard of Van Buren house, W. side of 14th St., between Fifth and Sixth Aves., 1911 May (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-3: Old houses, 15-17 Dominick Street, north side between Clark and Varick, 1910 Dec. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-4: S.W. corner Hudson and Christopher Sts., 1910 Dec. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-7: Greenwich Hall, 501 Hudson, N.W. corner of Hudson and Christopher Sts., looking up Hudson, row of 5 old houses adjoining hall, 1910 Dec. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-8: Fourth Ave. side of Madison Square Garden, between 26 and 27 Sts., 1911 June (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-9: Old shacks, N. side 64th St. west of Central Park West; 23 Crimmins Tavern, adjoining at 21 Central Park Gardens, 1911 Aug (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-10: Old wooden houses, N.W. corner of Jackson and Front Sts., corner 77 Jackson, 4 in block about to be torn down, 1911 Aug. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-11: Old Van Buren House and portion of yard looking east on 14th St., 1911 Aug. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-12: Old Schermerhorn House, University Place, 1911 May (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-13: Shanty and refreshment booth, S.E. corner of Fifth Ave. and 90th St., opposite Carnegie Museum [Moxie sign], 1911 Oct. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-14: Row of old houses, N. side Canal St., 461-473 Canal St. between Hudson and Varick Sts., 1910 Dec. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-15: 7 State St., and along State, looking East [Mission of Our Lady of the Rosary], 1911 Feb. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-16: Jones Lane at South Street, 53 South St. at N.W. corner, 1911 Feb. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-17: N.W. corner of South and DePeyster Sts., 1911 Feb. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-18: N.W. corner Wall and South Sts., 1911 Feb. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-19: 69-71 Charlton St., N. side, between Hudson and Varick Sts., 1910 Dec. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-20: Old homes, N. side of Bleecker St. facing Hancock, 207-209 Bleecker St., on N.E. corner at Minetta Lane, 1910 Dec. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-21: N.W. corner of Sullivan and Watts Sts., wooden buildings and junk shop, 1910 Dec. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-22: Colonnade row opposite Astor Library, 1911 Feb. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-23: Cushman's old store, N.E. corner of 10th St. and Greenwich Ave., looking down 10th St., 1911 Feb. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-24: Old Schermerhorn's Mansion, N. side of 23rd St. opposite Stern's; taken just as beginning to tear down, 1911 May (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-25: E. side of Beekman Place from 49th to 51st Sts., 1911 June (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-27: Old houses, 107-109 W. 11th St., E. of Fourth Ave., 1911 May (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-28: Old houses, 93-95 Morton St., N. side between Greenwich and Washington; torn down Spring 1911, 1910 Dec. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-71: [Spy Oak, Westchester], 1906 June (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-72-73: [Pell Oak, Bronx, Pelham Bay Park], 1906 June (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-76: [Big Elm, in front of Neal's store, Stockbridge, Mass.], 1904 Aug. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-77: [Big Elm and Casino, Stockbridge, Mass.], 1904 Aug. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-78: [Big Elm in front of Peck House, Stratford, Conn.], 1904 Aug. (Offsite-box 2)
    - C-79: [Elms on Main Street, Stockbridge, Mass.], 1904 Aug. (Offsite-box 2)
  - Subseries II.B. Unnumbered Prints
    - New York, NY - Street scenes, 1903-1913 June (Offsite-box 2)
      27 prints
    - New York, NY - Parks, 1901-1903 (Offsite-box 2)
      13 prints
    - New York, NY - Trees, 1901-1904 (Offsite-box 2)
      7 prints
    - Bronx, New York, 1901-1906 (Offsite-box 2)
      6 prints
    - Brooklyn, New York, Prospect Park, 1904, undated (Offsite-box 2)
      15 prints
    - Queens, New York, 1901, undated (Offsite-box 2)
      4 prints
    - Twilight Park, New York, 1909 (Offsite-box 2)
      24 prints
    - Westchester, New York, undated (Offsite-box 2)
      1 print
    - Connecticut, 1904, undated (Offsite-box 2)
    - Massachusetts, 1904, undated (Offsite-box 2)
    - Unidentified trees, 1903, undated (Offsite-box 2)
      11 prints